Guide to the Olaf Larson papers,1918-2001
Larson, Olaf papers, 1918-2001.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Olaf Larson papers, 1918-2001
21-33-1791
Olaf Larson
29.4 cubic ft.
Reports, records, correspondence, research notes, surveys and manuscripts.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Papers of Dr. Olaf Frederick Larson, professor of rural sociology.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Professor of rural sociology (retired), New York State College of Agriculture and Life Sciences, Cornell University.
Cornell University Ph.D. 1938.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes Department of Rural Sociology annual reports to the dean and budget records, 1918-1946; department research and extension reports; Larson's correspondence as head of the department, 1957-1966 and later correspondence; records of University committees chaired by Larson; material relating to the Rural Sociological Society; department historical material; and other papers of Olaf Frederick Larson.
Also, York Migrant Agricultural Working Studies(1957-1959); New York Community Study records (1924, 1930, 1936, 1974); other community studies; and files on the Northeast Regional Center for Rural Development (1972-1975).
SUBJECTS
Names:
Larson, Olaf.; Cornell University--Faculty.; New York State College of Agriculture and Life Sciences.Dept. of Rural Sociology.; Northeast Regional Center for Rural Development.; Rural Sociological Society.
Subjects:
Sociology, Rural--Study and teaching.; Migrant labor--New York (State); Migrant labor--Study and teaching.; College teachers.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Community Studies/Surveys
Boxes 10-14
Series II. Correspondence
Boxes 1-4, 10, 28-29
Series III. Department of Rural Sociology
Boxes 7, 15
Series IV. Extension
Boxes 5-6
Series V. Migrant Workers
Boxes 17-27
Series VI. Northeast Regional Center for Rural Development
Box 16
Series VII. Research
Boxes 9, 30
Series VIII. University Committees
Box 8
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Community Studies/Surveys
  Survey schedules completed for each of 13 New York communities in 1924, 1930, 1936, and 1974. The first three studies were made as part of a national sample of 140 American agricultural villages, the first by the Institute of Social and Religious Research, the second by the Institute in cooperation with President Hoover's Research Committee on social trends, and the third by the Columbia University Council for Research in the Social Sciences in cooperation with the Division of Farm Population and Rural Life, Bureau of Agricultural Economics, U.S. Department of Agriculture. The fourth was made by Joseph L. Richardson, a graduate student in rural sociology, and Olaf Larson.
  - Extension: Connecticut-West Virginia, 1973 (Box 10)
  - Surveys of Community Activities: A-Franklinville, 1923-1930 (Box 10)
  - Surveys of Community Activities: Alamont, 1923-1930 (Box 11)
  - Surveys of Community Activities: Honeoye Falls-Webster, 1923-1930 (Box 11)
  - New York Communities Survey, 1924-1977 (Box 12)
  - Richfield Springs, Van Hornesville Community Studies (These two districts were chosen by the Cornell Cooperative Extension Service for an experimental project in community development. The materials include reports by the special extension agents employed for the project, reports by community committees, reports of special studies made for the project, and material related to the community surveys.), 1947-1958 (Box 13-14)
- Series II. Correspondence
  - Aa-F, 1949-1965 (Box 1)
  - Gibson-Mial, 1951-1975 (Box 2)
  - Mo-Taylor, 1953-1973 (Box 3)
  - U-Z; specific research projects, 1942-1969 (Box 4)
  - A-Le, 1960-1996 (Box 28)
  - Li-Z, 1955-1993 (Box 29)
- Series III. Department of Rural Sociology
  - Department of Rural Sociology, 1959-1967 (Box 7)
  - Dept. of Rural Sociology records supplement; includes plaque and photos, 1946-1983 (Box 15)
- Series IV. Extension
  - Extension committees, 1954-1971 (Box 5)
  - Extension and Rural Sociology, 1945-1961 (Box 6)
- Series V. Migrant Workers
  - Camp Interviews, Crew Leader Interviews, Crew Leader Schedules, 1957-59 (Box 24)
  - Correspondence, memoranda, field notes, 1953-1968 (Box 19)
  - Correspondence, 1953-1959 (Box 22)
  - Semi-Monthly Summary Report, Florida counties, 1953-1959 (Box 22)
  - Correspondence, summary, work plan, 1953-1957 (Box 23)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 23)
  - Labor Registration Certificates, 1957-1965 (Box 17)
  - Labor Registration Certificates, 1965-1968 (Box 18)
  - Labor Registration Certificates, 1968 (Box 19)
  - Migrant Farm Labor Study papers (Box 27)
    - Negro Migratory Agricultural Workers: Change and Stability in the Atlantic Coast Stream (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - Migratory Farm Workers in the Atlantic Coast Stream: Wage Rates Paid to Migrant Workers, 1950s (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - Migratory Farm Workers - Crew Leaders, 1950s (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - Migrant Workers - Supervision and Management (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - Farm Camp Notes, 1957 (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - Worksheets on Unemployment, 1950s (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - Migratory Labor Study, 1953 (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - Migratory Farm Workers in NYS-operator schedule summary tables, 1959 (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - Sample, 1953 (Box 27, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 1960s (Box 27, Folder 10)
    - Housing, late 1950s -early 1960s (Box 27, Folder 11)
    - Migratory Farm Workers in the Atlantic Coast Stream - Housing and Technology, 1963 (Box 27, Folder 12)
    - Negro Migratory Agricultural Worker, 1950s (Box 27, Folder 13)
    - Migratory Farm Labor in NYS - Tables and Excerpts, 1953 (Box 27, Folder 14)
    - Farm Labor Study, 1957 (Box 27, Folder 15)
    - Farm Labor Study - Code Keys, 1958 (Box 27, Folder 16)
    - Farm Labor Study - Sample, 1958 (Box 27, Folder 17)
    - Migratory Farm Workers in NYS, 1957 (Box 27, Folder 18)
    - Migratory Farm workers in NYS, 1959 (Box 27, Folder 19)
    - Social Status and Farm Tenure - Social Conditions, 1938 (Box 27, Folder 20)
    - Sharecroppers and Wage Laborers, South Carolina Louisiana Farm Laborers and Total War, 1940 (Box 27, Folder 21)
    - Agricultural Labor Force in the San Joaquin Valley, California, USDA, 1942 (Box 27, Folder 22)
    - Hired Farm Workforce, USDA, 1948 (Box 27, Folder 23)
    - Hired Farm Workforce, USDA, 1948-1949 (Box 27, Folder 24)
    - Hired Farm Workforce, USDA, 1951-1952 (Box 27, Folder 25)
    - Hired Farm Workforce, USDA, 1964-1966 (Box 27, Folder 26)
    - Hired Farm Labor Data - limitations, 1975-1979 (Box 27, Folder 27)
    - Migratory Farm Workers in Atlantic Coast Stream: Changes in New York, 1983 (Box 27, Folder 28)
    - Migratory Farm Workers in Atlantic Coast Stream: Education of New York Workers and Their Children, 1953-1957 (Box 27, Folder 29)
    - Changes in Migrant Labor in New York, 1953-1957 (Box 27, Folder 30)
    - Rural Poverty in the U.S., 1965 (Box 27, Folder 31)
    - Farm Labor's Niche in History, 1968 (Box 27, Folder 32)
    - Farm Working Force, 1976 (Box 27, Folder 33)
    - Migratory Farm Workers: A Problem in Migratory Analysis, 1943 (Box 27, Folder 34-35)
    - Cultural Factors Which Result in Artificial Labor Shortages, 1943 (Box 27, Folder 36)
    - Wages of Agricultural Labor in the U.S. - USDA, 1945 (Box 27, Folder 37)
    - New York's Harvest Labor, 1943-1948 (Box 27, Folder 38)
    - Farm & Food Processing Labor Annual Report - NY DOL, 1958 (Box 27, Folder 39)
    - NYS Interdepartmental Committee on Migrant Labor, 1969-1970 (Box 27, Folder 40)
    - FSA-BRE Farm Labor Studies, 1937 (Box 27, Folder 41)
    - FP.RL - Farm Wage Stabilization, 1946-1948 (Box 27, Folder 42)
    - Farm Wage Rates Study - Reports, 1946 (Box 27, Folder 43)
    - Farm Wage Rates Study - Reports, 1946 (Box 27, Folder 44)
    - Farm Wage Rates Study - Reports, 1945-1946 (Box 27, Folder 45)
  - Operator schedules, 1958-1959 (Box 25)
  - Operator schedules, 1959 (Box 26)
  - Labor Registration Certificates, 1953-1958 (Box 26)
  - Index cards of living conditions (Box 26)
  - New York farm labor bulletins, 1957-1967 (Box 21)
  - Various tables, 1957-1967 (Box 21)
  - State code sheets, 1957-1967 (Box 21)
  - Survey material and code sheets, 1953-1959 (Box 20)
- Series VI. Northeast Regional Center for Rural Development
  The Northeast Regional Center for Rural Development was established in 1972 under the Rural Development Act of 1972. It was located at Cornell by action of the agricultural experiment station directors and the extension directors of the 12 Northeastern states. It was one of four such centers in the United States. Olaf Larson was the Director during 1972-75. The material pertains to the work of the Center, its Board of Directors, its Technical Committee, and the special committees during his tenure. The files of Nyle Brady, Director of the CUAES at the time and chair of the Board of Directors, and the file of David Call, Director of Cooperative Extension at Cornell at the time, may also include material relating to the Center. A few years ago the Center was relocated to the Pennsylvania State University where it continues to be active.
  - Northeast Center for Rural Development, 1970-1976 (Box 16)
- Series VII. Research
  - Research, 1944-1967 (Box 9)
  - Research projects, 1947-2001 (Box 30)
    - Administration and Reports, 1955-82 (Box 30, Folder 1-2)
    - Hatch Act and Purnell, 1947-67 (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - Research Projects, 1947-61 (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - The Town of Richfield - A collection of Local History Articles (pgs. 73-75) written by Olaf Larson, 1961 (Box 30)
    - Research Projects, 1957-67 (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - Research Projects, 1958-67 (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - Agricultural Policy Research Committee-Rural Sociological Society (Box 30, Folder 7)
    - Committee on the Development of Rural Sociology (Box 30, Folder 8)
    - Richfield Springs Project, 1948,1958 (Box 30, Folder 9)
    - Polson, Robert, 1948-1997 (Box 30, Folder 10)
    - State Project 39 (Taber) Research Review on Comparative Community Project July 5, 1968, 1963-1984 (Box 30, Folder 11)
    - Levine, Joseph Jonathan, 1967-68 (Box 30, Folder 12)
    - Black Experience - requests sent for CRIS publications, data, 1976-77 (Box 30, Folder 13)
    - "The Predominately Black Counties of 1930: A Comparative Analysis of Social-Economics Change and Agricultural Policy" by Minnie Brown and Olaf Larson, 1982 (Box 30, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, 1981-86 (Box 30, Folder 15)
    - Congressional Black Caucus - notes, programs, 1986 (Box 30, Folder 16)
    - Publicity-Black Experience in Agriculture, 1980s (Box 30, Folder 17)
    - Papers: "The World Agriculture Society, 1919-1927: The Beginnings of International Rural Development Organizations" 1989; "Sociology and Government: the Case of Rural Sociology in the US Dept. of Agriculture, 1919-53" 1992; "Left Undone: Past History, Future Research" 1996; notes from 1989 presentation, 1989,1992, 1996 (Box 30, Folder 18)
    - ASA paper - "Pioneering in the Development and Practice of Sociology by the USDA", 1990 (Box 30, Folder 19)
    - ASA- D'Antonio, William, 1988-92 (Box 30, Folder 20)
    - ASA - Howery, Carla, 1988-90 (Box 30, Folder 21)
    - Brown, David, 1987-91 (Box 30, Folder 22)
    - Foster, Arnold, 1987-90 (Box 30, Folder 23)
    - Hickey, Anthony, 1987-88 (Box 30, Folder 24)
    - Holik, John, 1988-92 (Box 30, Folder 25)
    - Johnson, Mrs. Helen, 1973-94 (Box 30, Folder 26)
    - Loomis, Dr. Charles, 1987-88 (Box 30, Folder 27)
    - Martin, Margaret E., 1987 (Box 30, Folder 28)
    - Moe, Edward, 1987-95 (Box 30, Folder 29)
    - National Agricultural Library-Special Collections- Correspondence, 1992-01 (Box 30, Folder 30)
    - Sanders, Irwin, 1992-94 (Box 30, Folder 31)
    - Taeuber, Conrad, 1986-95 (Box 30, Folder 32)
    - Wiser, Vivian, 1987-92 (Box 30, Folder 33)
    - Correspondence - B-W, 1988-96 (Box 30, Folder 34)
    - Dedication of the Polson Institute for Global Development, 2001 (Box 30, Folder 35)
- Series VIII. University Committees
  - College of Agriculture, Cornell University, 1949-1971 (Box 8)